Finding Aid for the Miriam Matthews papers LSC.1804
UCLA Library Special Collections
Miriam Matthews papers
1845-1988, bulk 1920-1980
1920-1980
UCLA Library Special Collections
Matthews, Miriam
LSC.1804
11.5 linear feet (23 boxes, 2 oversize boxes)
Miriam Matthews (1905-2003), the first credentialed African-American librarian in the state of California, was a librarian at Los Angeles Public Library (1927-1960), a historian of African American and California history, and an active member of the American and California Library Associations' Committees on Intellectual Freedom. The collection consists of clippings, correspondence, photographs, reports, ephemera, and other materials relating to intellectual freedom; the Los Angeles Public Library; Matthews' involvement with professional, civic, community, and historical organizations; and her research on African-American and California history.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Miriam Matthews family, 2008.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9961542473606533
We are committed to providing ethical, inclusive, and anti-racist description of the materials we steward, and to remediating existing description of our materials that contains language that may be offensive or cause harm. We invite you to submit feedback about how our collections are described, and how they could be described more accurately, by filling out the form located on our website: Report Potentially Offensive Description in Library Special Collections.
Biography
Miriam Matthews (1905-2003), the first credentialed African-American librarian in the state of California, was a librarian at Los Angeles Public Library (1927-1960), a historian of African American and California history, and an active member of the American and California Library Associations' Committees on Intellectual Freedom.
Miriam Matthews was born on August 6, 1905 in Pensacola, Florida and moved to Los Angeles with her family two years later. After graduating from Los Angeles High School in 1922, Matthews studied at the University of California, Southern Branch (now UCLA) for two years. She transferred to the University of California, Berkeley where she graduated with a B.A. in 1926 and a certificate in librarianship in 1927, becoming the first known certified African American librarian in California. Matthews began her career at the Los Angeles Public Library (LAPL) in 1927 and became a branch librarian in 1934. She took two leaves of absence from LAPL, one in 1940 to work at the New York Public Library in a librarian exchange program and another from 1944 to 1945 in order to earn a master's degree in library science from the University of Chicago. In 1949, she was promoted to regional librarian, a position she held until her retirement from LAPL in 1960.
Matthews was one of the first people to advocate for the establishment of Negro History Week (now African American History Month) in Los Angeles, leading to its official observance by the City of Los Angeles in 1931. In 1946, she became chairman of the California Library Association Committee on Intellectual Freedom. The following year, she was appointed to the American Library Association Committee on Intellectual Freedom (1947-1951) where she contributed to the 1948 revision of the Library Bill of Rights. In 1977, Gov. Edmund Brown appointed Matthews to the California Heritage Preservation Commission and California State Historic Records Advisory Board. She contributed to the establishment of an archives and records management program for the City of Los Angeles in 1979. While a member of the Los Angeles 200 Committee in 1981, Matthews proposed and implemented the construction of a historical plaque detailing the names, ages, and races of the city founders.
Matthews died in Mercer Island, Washington on June 23, 2003.
In 2003, the Los Angeles Historical Society established the annual Miriam Matthews Award in her honor. The Los Angeles Public Library Hyde Park branch was renamed for her in 2004.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of clippings, correspondence, photographs, reports, ephemera, and other materials relating to intellectual freedom; Matthews' work at Los Angeles Public Library; her involvement with professional, civic, community, and historical organizations; and her research on African American and California history. The collection is especially strong in materials about Titus Alexander, Ralph J. Bunche, Mary Ellen Pleasant, and William Grant Still.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Committee work and professional memberships
Los Angeles Public Library
Personal papers
Subject files.
Original file titles were preserved whenever possible.
Related Oral History
The following oral history is available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Interview of Miriam Matthews
Related Material
Miriam Matthews Collection. African American Museum and Library at Oakland (AAMLO).
Miriam Matthews Photographic Collection. California African American Museum, Los Angeles.
African American women librarians -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Matthews, Miriam -- Archives; Bunche, Ralph J. (Ralph Johnson); Pleasant, Mary Ellen; Still, William Grant, 1895-1978.
- Committee Work and Professional Memberships, 1943-1980
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, agendas, minutes, newsletters and publications, newspaper articles, grant proposals and evaluations, and recommendations relating to Miriam Matthews's involvement on committees and boards
  - American Library Association--conference, 1953 June 21-25, probably 1949. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    American Library Association resolution, constitution, conference reporter, program.
  - American Library Association--Intellectual Freedom Committee, 1946-1950. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Clippings, correspondence, and organization's resolutions on censorship, loyalty oath.
  - American Library Association--Intellectual Freedom Committee, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence, memoranda, clippings, pamphlets.
  - American Library Association--Intellectual Freedom Committee, 1952-1964. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondence, clippings, organizations' resolutions about censorship and teaching UNESCO curriculum in Los Angeles schools.
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Grant proposal--Oakland Museum.
  - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), 1952-1953, 1965-1972. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Civil Liberties, publication of ACLU
  - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), 1946-1953, 1965-1972. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Open Forum, publication of ACLU Southern California Branch
  - American Library Association, 1943, 1953, 1965-1982. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Bulletins and conference program.
  - American Library Association--Intellectual Freedom Committee, 1947-1953. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Correspondence, newspaper articles, pamphlets, notes, conference program, reading lists.
  - American Library Association--Newsletter on Intellectual Freedom, 1953-1979. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - American Library Association--nominees, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - California Library Association, 1949,1967-1975. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - California Library Association--Committee on Intellectual Freedom, 1948. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - California Library Association--conferences, 1953 November 11-14, 1984 December 1-5. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Calibrarian, 1957, 1967-1975. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Newsletters.
  - Developmental Reading Committee, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - California Heritage Preservation Commission, 1977-1980. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, minutes, agenda, memoranda.
  - California Heritage Preservation Commission, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Correspondence and reports regarding State Archives Building and drafts of Governor's Records Act.
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1977-1978. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Correspondence, agenda, evaluations.
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Correspondence, minutes, agenda
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Grant proposals, evaluations.
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Grant proposals.
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Recommendations to National Historical Publications and Records Commission.
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Grant proposal.
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1978. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Recommendations to National Historical Publications and Records.
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1979. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1980. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - California State Historical Records Advisory Board, 1980. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Public Library Association, 1971 March, 1975 October. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Society of California Archivists, 1977-1978. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Newsletters, annual meeting, newspaper articles.
- Los Angeles Public Library, 1937-1973 (bulk 1937-1959)
  Memos, bulletins, reports, and surveys by or for Los Angeles Public Library staff. Series also includes administrative reports and work produced by Miriam Matthews in her positions as branch and regional librarian.
  - California Library Tax Report, 1939-1941. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Compiled by Special Committee of Los Angeles Public Library staff.
  - Los Angeles Public Library Regional Librarians, 1956-1959. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Memoranda, reports, meeting minutes.
  - Los Angeles Public Library, 1941-1957. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Reports.
  - Vermont Square Library branch history, undated. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    History of the branch 1913-1949.
  - El Pueblo, 1965-1972. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    All City Employees Association newsletter.
  - Los Angeles Public Library, 1951-1959. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Memoranda, bulletins, reports
  - Los Angeles Public Library, 1943-1959, 1972-1976. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    News bulletins, flyers, clippings, statistics, reports.
  - Los Angeles Public Library School, 1934. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Photocopy of alumni directory.
- Subject Files, 1845-1988
  Subject files collected by Matthews that documents people and organizations, particularly relating to Los Angeles, California, and African American history.
  - Africa, 1950-1976, undated. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Bibliographies, pamphlets, newsletters, clippings.
  - Alexander, Titus, 1917-1951, undated. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Clippings, memo book with handwritten notes probably belonging to Titus Alexander, handwritten biographical notes by Miriam Matthews.
  - Archy Lee slave case, 1858. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Microfilmed clipping.
  - Bass, Charlotta A., 1960, 1969. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Photocopy of last will and testament and court papers.
  - Beal, Israel, 1929 May 13. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Negro pioneer of Redlands, California. Photocopy of clipping.
  - Beckwourth, James, 1938, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Articles.
  - Black Americans, 1966-1980, undated. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Map, United States Department of Labor publication, clippings, pamphlets.
  - Adams Chronicles, 1975. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Guide for public television series, clipping.
  - Alexander, Titus, 1923-1981, predominantly 1923-1953. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Originals and photocopies of published articles about Titus Alexander. Many articles are not dated. Photographs of Miriam Matthews are in Church and Community Press, 1953 and Los Angeles Tribune, 1952 June 13.
  - Alexander, Titus, circa 1933-1948. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Speeches.
  - Alexander, Titus, undated. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Writings and notes.
  - Alexander, Titus, 1917-1956. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Correspondence.
  - Alexander, Titus, circa 1917-1981. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Biographical sketches about Titus Alexander, photographs, Western Pennsylvania Medical College matriculation card, business cards, marriage announcement.
  - Alexander, Titus, 1913-1958, undated. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Event programs, invitations, Palomar Observatory, correspondence mentioning or endorsing Titus Alexander, political articles and pamphlets, poems by others, pamphlets about rights and contributions of colored Americans, shares of Charleston National Mining Company owned by Lara B. Allens.
  - Alexander, Titus, circa 1910-1936. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Photo album probably belonging to Titus Alexander. Photographs of unidentified children and adults, some at Yosemite. Titus Alexander is likely pictured in some photographs.
  - Allen, Edgar, 1977-1982. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Handwritten Edgar Allen retirement speech by Miriam Matthews, correspondence and memoranda regarding City of Los Angeles records management and archives.
  - Allensworth, California, 1912, 1968-1978. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Copy of newspaper article, water system dedication program.
  - American Lung Association of Los Angeles County, 1980 May 13. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Memorandum regarding Proposition 9 on California ballet.
  - American Society of African Culture, 1959 November - 1966 February. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Anderson, Fred, 1976, 1980. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    University of Southern California dissertation, correspondence.
  - Art, 1965, 1966, undated. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Clippings, programs.
  - Association for Study of Negro Life and History, 1968-1978, undated. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Convention materials, bulletins, pamphlets, clippings, advertisement.
  - Ayers, Carolyn, 1988 December 27. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bogle, Richard and America Waldo, circa 1980-1981. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Letter and copies of newspaper clippings about history of Richard Bogle and his family.
  - Biographies of Black Americans, undated. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Biographical sketches of Daniel Hale Williams, George Washington Carver, James Weldon Johnson, Sojourner Truth, Crispus Attucks, Phyllis Wheatley, Ralph Johnson Bunche, Martin Luther King, Blanche Kelso Bruce, Langston Hughes.
  - Blacks in Los Angeles, 1966-circa 1984. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Black History Month reception program, Los Angeles Riot Study article information, clippings.
  - Black librarians, contemporary, 1969, 1978. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    American Libraries and University of Chicago Magazine articles.
  - Black librarians, history and biographies, 1939-1983, predominantly 1966-1975. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    California Librarians Black Caucus meeting minutes. Articles about Edward C. Williams, George W. Forbes, Thomas F. Blue, Daniel A.P. Murray, Robert Wedgeworth, Loyce Pleasants, Effie Lee Morris, Sadie P. Delaney, Joseph H. Reason, Clara Stanton Jones, Harriet B. Brown, Janette Smith.
  - Black newspapers, 1931-1943, 1964-1973. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Photostats of black and mainstream Los Angeles newspapers articles. Includes John Fowler's Spreading Joy column in the California Eagle.
  - Black performers, 1940-1978. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Clippings.
  - Black scientists, 1945-1974, undated. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Clipping, Tuskegee Institute annual report, biographical booklet of Black American scientists.
  - Book history, undated. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Clipping and University of California, Berkeley class brochure.
  - Bradley, Tom, 1969-1973, undated. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Los Angeles Councilman report, mayoral campaign materials, clippings.
  - Browning, Ivan Harold, 1978-1980. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    Newspaper article, tribute concert program.
  - Bulletins--miscellaneous, 1952-1984. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Bunche, Ralph J., 1922-1978, predominantly 1949-1978. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Addresses and programs for events featuring or in memoriam of Ralph Bunche. Includes program of Jefferson High School graduation.
  - Bunche, Ralph J., 1927-1972. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bunche, Ralph J., 1973-1974. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bunche, Ralph J., 1975-1976. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - California history, 1930-1984. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Pamphlets, newsletters, articles.
  - California state reports, 1975-1981. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    "Identification of the Historical Records of County Government in California" and "The Preservation, Organization and Display of California's Historic Documents."
  - Churches--First A.M.E.--Los Angeles, 1921, 1953-1986, undated. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Originals and photocopies of programs, correspondence and articles.
  - Churches--First A.M.E.--Pasadena, circa 1975. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Photocopy of dedication program.
  - Churches--Independent Church, 1915-1966, undated. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Copies of programs and history of the church. Typescripts of articles, handwritten notes, photographs.
  - Churches--United Church of Christ, 1978. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Newsletter.
  - Churches--Ward Chapel A.M.E., 1951 February 5. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Clipping.
  - "Citizen's guide to collection of source materials in Negro history", undated. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Paper written by Wesley Brazier, Lawrence de Graaf, Norman O. Houston, Miriam Matthews, and Vassie Wright, members of Committee to Preserve California Negro History.
  - Cloud, Frank, 1915-1931, undated. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of his Crisis magazine covers of photographs taken by Cloud Studios.
  - Collection checklists, undated. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Checklists of contents of Jessie L. Terry Collection, Bessie Bruington Burke Collection, and Biddy Mason Collection.
  - Compton, California, 1964 August, 1973 December. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Conference of California Historical Societies, 1982-1983. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Crisis, 1922 August, 1976 May. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - De Graaf, Lawrence, 1969. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Copy of de Graaf's research paper, "Black Los Angeles: Making of a ghetto."
  - Delta Sigma Theta, 1929, 1974-1984. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Newsletters, newspaper photograph, event program.
  - Dodson, Jacob, 1964 November. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    Negro History Bulletin article, "The Negro Who Rode with Fremont in 1847."
  - Elizabeth Fry Center, 1976 May. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    California Senate bill appeal.
  - Equality in employment, 1962-1963, undated. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Government and private industry brochures and publications.
  - Equality in employment, 1966-1968, 1984, undated. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Ethiopian Students Union in North America, 1974. (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Paper, "Mass organizations"
  - Exceptional Children's Foundation, 1971 October. (Box 9, Folder 16)
    Fundraising invitation with handwritten notes.
  - Family Savings and Loan, 1964-1976. (Box 9, Folder 17)
    Financial statements, newsletter article.
  - Fisher, James A., 1969 December, 1971 September, undated. (Box 9, Folder 18)
    Writings.
  - Foster, David, undated. (Box 9, Folder 19)
    Signed pencil drawing by David Foster.
  - Franklin, John Hope, 1976. (Box 9, Folder 20)
    Jefferson Lecture in the Humanities program and newspaper article.
  - Gafford, Alice, 1942, 1961, 1967, 1971, 1972. (Box 9, Folder 21)
    Clippings, program, correspondence.
  - Golden State International Exposition, 1939. (Box 9, Folder 22)
    Souvenir program.
  - Golden State Minority Foundation, 1976-1985, undated. (Box 9, Folder 23)
    Programs, newsletters, brochures.
  - Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1975, 1976, undated. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Publications and industry articles.
  - Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1974 December - 1977 October. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Golden Pen newsletter
  - Grant, M. Earl, 1968 February. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Griffith, Harold, 1985 March 10. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Grandson of Griffith van Griffith. Obituary
  - Grimes, Leonard, 1977. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Address of Congregational Church of Christian Fellowship, note to Miriam Matthews.
  - Haiti, 1967 December 25. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Hart, Philip, 1983. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    California Council for the Humanities grant proposal, "In Search of a Dream, Early California Black Aviators."
  - Hayden, Dolores, 1987, 1988. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Paper, "Biddy Mason's Los Angeles, 1856-1891." Program of "The Life and Times of Biddy Mason."
  - Historical societies--California, 1971-1985. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Newsletters and ephemera.
  - Housing--California, 1949-1984. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Pamphlets and reports on housing desegregation, newsletter.
  - Housing--Los Angeles, 1951-1958, 1967-1968, undated. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    Mimeographs of segregation announcement and integration advertisements. Pamphlets and reports on housing desegregation.
  - Johnson, Dorothy Vena, 1961-1976, undated. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Correspondence, history of Garden Gate High School, drafts of biographical sketch written by Miriam Matthews, clippings.
  - Johnson, Dorothy Vena, undated. (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Copies of her poetry, bibliography of her works.
  - League of Allied Arts, 1938-1981. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Event programs, newspaper articles, correspondence, photographs of Calvin Bailey.
  - Legal Defense Fund, 1975-1984, undated. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Ephemera, articles.
  - Liberty Savings and Loan Association, 1924-1960. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of newsletters, financial statement.
  - Links, Los Angeles Chapter, 1956, 1960. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Cotillion and souvenir programs.
  - Links, Los Angeles Chapter, 1964-1972, undated.. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Cotillion programs. Constitution and bylaws.
  - Lomax, Almena, 1961-1968. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of short stories.
  - Los Angeles County Commission on Human Relations, 1955-1973. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Proposition 21 report, letter, newsletter, pamphlet.
  - Los Angeles historical landmarks, 1944-1979, undated. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Lists of registered landmarks, history of missions.
  - Los Angeles history, 1958-1977, undated. (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Articles, clippings.
  - Los Angeles 200, 1980. (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Letter.
  - Los Angeles Urban Archives, California State University, Northridge, 1979. (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Copy of report and grant proposal.
  - Modern Maturity magazine, 1978-1980. (Box 11, Folder 12)
    articles
  - Morgan, Charles, undated. (Box 11, Folder 13)
    Excerpts from "The Fountain." Handwritten excerpts from "Private Worlds" by Phyllis Bottonie.
  - Morris, Louise Fisher, 1977, undated. (Box 11, Folder 14)
    Photocopies of photographs and biographical sketch.
  - National Council on Public History, 1983-1986. (Box 11, Folder 15)
    Pamphlets and newsletters.
  - Negro and democracy, 1940-1949, undated. (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Pamphlets and bibliographies on civil rights, democracy, and discrimination.
  - Negro and democracy, 1950-1971, undated. (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Pamphlets and articles from the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
  - Negro and race relations, 1945-1967. (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Pamphlets, newsletters, clippings.
  - Negro bibliographies, 1925-1939. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Negro bibliographies, 1940-1956. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Negro in California--art and music events, 1946-1947, 1966-1977, 1987, undated. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Negro in California--articles, 1921-1976, undated. (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Clippings and copies of published writings.
  - Negro in California--community events, 1912, 1942-1977. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Clippings, programs, pamphlets.